<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Home on Saurav Shrivastav</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Home on Saurav Shrivastav</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 12:26:28 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to AI Engineering</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/ai-eng-intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 12:26:28 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/blog/ai-eng-intro/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been exploring AI Engineering recently—a field that sits right at the intersection of software engineering and data science. This post is the first in a series where I&amp;rsquo;ll share my notes and learnings as I dig deeper into what it takes to build production-ready AI systems.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h1 id=&#34;what-is-ai-engineering&#34;&gt;What is AI Engineering?&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;AI Engineering is about making AI work in the real world. It bridges the gap between theoretical research and practical application. While data science focuses on model accuracy and discovery, AI engineering focuses on &lt;strong&gt;reliability, scalability, and maintainability&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- &lt;div class=&#34;about-header&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;div class=&#34;about-text&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;p&gt;I&#39;m &lt;span class=&#34;highlight-name&#34;&gt;Saurav Shrivastav&lt;/span&gt;, a software engineer who believes that the best way to understand complex systems is to build them. Currently working on Hadoop infrastructure at LinkedIn in Bangalore, I&#39;ve spent my career scaling distributed systems and contributing to open source projects.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/div&gt;&#xA;    &lt;div class=&#34;about-image&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/profile.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Saurav Shrivastav&#34; class=&#34;profile-photo&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&#xA;## My Journey&#xA;&#xA;My journey into software engineering began at Thapar Institute of Engineering &amp; Technology, where I discovered my passion for building systems that solve real problems. College was transformative - I led the Google Developer Student Club (GDSC), where I organized hackathons, gave talks, and worked on small projects to solve problems with software. Most importantly, I found incredible mentors who shaped my approach to both technology and leadership.&#xA;&#xA;During college, I actively sought out internship opportunities at any company that would have me. Each experience, no matter how small, taught me something valuable about the industry and helped me grow as an engineer. The highlight was participating in Google Summer of Code with PostgreSQL, which opened my eyes to the world of open source and large-scale database systems.&#xA;&#xA;This foundation led me to LinkedIn, first as an intern and eventually to my current full-time role. The transition from college projects to handling millions of records in production systems has been both challenging and incredibly rewarding.&#xA;&#xA;## What I Do Today&#xA;&#xA;At LinkedIn, I work on fascinating problems in Hadoop infrastructure:&#xA;- Building automated cluster expansion systems that scale seamlessly&#xA;- Creating inventory management systems that track complex state transitions across production environments  &#xA;- Designing event-driven architectures using Kafka and pub-sub patterns&#xA;- Ensuring systems remain reliable while handling massive data workloads&#xA;&#xA;My open source journey continues with contributions to projects like PostgreSQL and OpenWISP, keeping me connected to the broader engineering community.&#xA;&#xA;## Beyond Code&#xA;&#xA;When I&#39;m not debugging distributed systems, you&#39;ll find me:&#xA;- **On the field**: Playing football (my favorite sport) or the occasional badminton match&#xA;- **On the road**: Exploring places on my motorcycle with friends - recently rode to Coonoor, Kotagiri, and Yercaud. Some of my most memorable adventures include longer trips to Sissu and Tosh in the past&#xA;- **Getting active**: Recently trying to get into running (still working on building that habit!)&#xA;- **Deep in papers**: Reading research papers to understand the theoretical foundations behind the systems I build&#xA;- **Writing**: Sharing experiences and learnings to help other engineers navigate similar challenges&#xA;&#xA;## My Philosophy&#xA;&#xA;I believe in learning through building and teaching. Every system I work on teaches me something new, and every research paper I read opens up new possibilities. My time leading GDSC taught me that the best way to grow is by helping others grow too.&#xA;&#xA;I&#39;m convinced that the most robust solutions come from understanding both the theoretical foundations and the practical constraints. Whether it&#39;s designing a distributed system or mentoring a junior engineer, I try to balance complexity with simplicity.&#xA;&#xA;## What&#39;s Next&#xA;&#xA;While I&#39;m deeply rooted in distributed systems and infrastructure, I&#39;m excited about exploring AI/ML next. The intersection of large-scale data processing and machine learning presents fascinating challenges that I&#39;m eager to dive into.&#xA;&#xA;## Why This Space&#xA;&#xA;I created this site to document my learning journey and share insights from working with distributed systems at scale. From my early days figuring out internships to now handling production systems at LinkedIn, I&#39;ve learned that sharing knowledge makes all of us better engineers.&#xA;&#xA;Whether you&#39;re here for the technical blog posts, the research paper deep dives, or just curious about the journey, I hope you find something useful for your own path in software engineering. --&gt;&#xA;&lt;div class=&#34;about-header&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;div class=&#34;about-text&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;p&gt;I&#39;m &lt;span class=&#34;highlight-name&#34;&gt;Saurav Shrivastav&lt;/span&gt;, a software engineer who believes that the best way to understand complex systems is to build them. Currently, I engineer Hadoop/YARN infrastructure at **LinkedIn** in Bangalore, where I design distributed orchestration platforms to manage a fleet of **80,000+ nodes**.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Contact</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/contact/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d love to hear from you! Whether you want to discuss technology, collaborate on a project, or just say hello, feel free to reach out through any of the channels below.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;get-in-touch&#34;&gt;Get in Touch&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;-email&#34;&gt;📧 Email&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For detailed discussions, collaboration proposals, or professional inquiries&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:sauravsrivastav103@gmail.com&#34;&gt;sauravsrivastav103@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;-linkedin&#34;&gt;💼 LinkedIn&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For professional networking and career-related conversations&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/saurav-shrivastav/&#34;&gt;linkedin.com/in/sauravsrivastav&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;-github&#34;&gt;⚡ GitHub&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Check out my code, open issues, or start discussions about my projects&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Saurav-Shrivastav&#34;&gt;github.com/Saurav-Shrivastav&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;-twitter&#34;&gt;🐦 Twitter&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For quick questions, tech discussions, or just to say hi&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://x.com/_saurav_23&#34;&gt;@_saurav_23&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
